foreign
[Music]
all right hello and welcome everyone
this is actinf live stream number 47.0
it is august 3rd 2022
welcome to the active inference
institute
we are a participatory online lab and
institute that is communicating learning
and practicing applied active inference
you can find us at some of the links on
the slide
this is a recorded and an archived and
transcribed and published live
so please provide us with feedback
so we can improve our work
all backgrounds and perspectives are
welcome and we'll be following video
etiquette for live streams
all active inference institute
activities are participatory so do let
us know if you want to contribute or get
involved head over to
activeinference.org and click the links
to participate directly and to learn
more
well
we are about to set off on a
odd-numbered
and unique adventure in 47.
we're going to be discussing and
juxtaposing not one paper as per usual
but have a multiple eyes open approach
towards two papers in this situation
we're going to be learning and
discussing
in a juxtaposed fashion two papers
active inference and abduction in 2021
by ati vaiko
pieteren and majid beni
also we'll be discussing an active
dynamic social cognition and active
inference by ines hippolyto and thomas
van s also from 2021
all videos
dot zeros and otherwise are
introductions to these ideas and
additional context not a review or
evaluation or final word
and we are going to
consistently we hope use this coloration
of a light red for the abductive paper
and a light blue for the inactive
leaving the space open for new colors
and combinations to arise that
demonstrate some areas of synthesis
and we're gonna talk in this dot zero
with some big questions and go over our
aims as well as reading in between those
aims which is a little bit different
than many live streams
we're then going to provide
overview information on each paper in
terms of aims the claims the roadmap and
the abstract
we'll then move to a background in
context section
that will include a lot of information
on inaction semiotics abductive logic
and so on
we'll then move into a juxtaposition of
the two papers
and we're going to have a lot of time to
discuss with hopefully multiple authors
in the upcoming
discussions.1.2 and maybe beyond so
today we wanted to bring a big picture
context
talk about some very interesting threads
provide a little bit of background that
helps one enter into this space and then
provide an initial juxtaposition and run
through these papers that again will
just get somebody excited to read the
papers dive in more deeply and bring
their own perspective to bear on these
very interesting topics
so
we'll move to the introductions
i'm daniel i'm a researcher in
california
and i'll talk more about what's exciting
in the coming slides i'll pass it to
dean
uh good morning my name is dean i'm in
calgary and uh i guess i was
maybe the the warped mind that tried to
put this idea together and maybe
change a little bit the way that we look
at active inference by trying to pull
two different papers of seeming
seemingly
different folk focuses
and then
both of those also
incorporating the use of active
inferences as a methodology
to situationally analyze and so what are
the implications for that
so i find that really kind of exciting
and i'll pass it over to stephen
so thank you dean yes stephen here i'm
in um toronto canada um
and i'm really
interested about both of these papers
because
they both speak a lot to kind of
participatory
approaches in general and the idea of
how people are engaging in the world
um so the the questions around
um inaction
is is really relevant as is the
abduction piece so
um
while they're both quite different
papers the they're both
speaking
uh to me quite strongly so that's really
interesting so i'm looking forward to
being able to
sort of explore that i'm i'm i work with
uh participatory theater
community psychology community
development and multi-scale
development processes and i'm really
excited to
to just see how
this scientific take
can meet a more
what might be called a practice-based
participatory question that i've been
looking at so i'll pass it back to
daniel
excellent thank you both and dean thanks
again for the many month
journey
the many email and month
and message journey that we've walked
because i i do hope this will
unfold and include in a way that is
taking the live streams
and the kind of materials that we're
working through beyond where we have
gone
and
in
spirit of that i will pass the dean to
introduce some of the big questions here
well
if you're gonna pull two papers that
don't seem to have
a heck of a lot in common in terms of
their subject matter you're gonna have
to come at it from a little bit of a
different angle in terms of not just
ferreting out what's within a paper but
how those papers might be
compared so we pulled together some some
questions around the idea
of what role as a situational analysis
either tool or
reality method active inference might
play in
pulling things that seem to be a long
ways away and apart and entangle them
and so the questions were basically can
active inference be both
something that holds or contains or
bounds something and also be the thing
bounded or being gripped what is active
inference or if what if active emphasis
both the thing
being contained
um say a partitioner line in a table
and a cell
so that the actual gap that we can
actually put more information into what
that look like what it would look like
both as a constraint and a separator
simultaneously and i think it's that
mutuality piece that we're going to try
to tease out in the next few live
streams and what is similar or different
in getting a grip
on models and a different process which
is modeling
thank you steven do you want to add
anything here
no i think that
that covers a lot of it the only thing
that that x that's there is is sort of
denoting
you know can active inference models
modeling
um frameworks so this this this
contextualization of the term um sort of
comes into play but we're going to talk
about that a bit later so yeah thanks
awesome and
this is
one of potentially the first our aims
slides because
it is hopefully going to help to come
back to this level
the meme
here represents this live stream
bringing together
the two papers in a way where we've had
one hand clapping
now we're gonna bring that together into
two you can hear the sound coming out of
the live stream already especially if
you're listening
dean what would you describe about r
ames or how would you
um summarize oh and one other note i'll
add about rna ames is we want it to be
comprehensive but also to have videos
that are listenable and of reasonable
temporal duration so there will be many
slides that will have a lot of text
copied out of the paper and will merely
note pause the video if you'd like to
read but we're just going to move on
from many of the text slides we just
really wanted to make sure that all the
text was there invisible but we're not
going to read everything so
please dean uh summarize what of these
aims you'd like to
talk about you know i'm just going to
talk about the sort of the the
the root of each one of these bullets
which is take a closer look at the
realism instrument instrumentalism
debate i don't have to go into what that
is if you've been a participant in it
you know what we're describing
uh reinforce a two eyes open approach
where one eye takes in the pair of
active inference papers the inactive
dynamic social condition
and abduction while the other man if the
other eye manifests active inferences
as an integrator of both
because we think that it actually can do
that without blending
it can actually cause a weave or a braid
and then the third bullet is make
explicit the absolute necessity if we're
going to do those first two things of
understanding the temporal depth of
models that would actually
incorporate
two papers of seeming distant
topics as we make active inference into
two different subjects
and then just what we did is pulled out
different um
things that the authors noted about
their papers
thank you and stephen if you could carry
forth with reading in between those aims
or adding anything you'd like from this
slide
yeah thanks daniel so
you know one set of authors says you
know is really looking at
instrumentalism
and you know you know it's a valid
scientific perspective but you know
there is there then describes you know
this question about the road towards
um
realism
and normalism so
you know where
the idea is that in
one paper that instrumentalism is is is
the way to sort of
capture or to
to sort of hold ourselves in this
scientific work
well that can be challenged um
and we would we would see ways that we
might need to
to loosen that when we get into
participatory approaches so something in
between which loosens that scientific
space and is a practice space so the
same with the second point
um
where okay is is instrumentalism
um you know the way forward so what what
constitutes
behaviors when living in a niche what
constitutes living beings
um and how do we resolve
which way forward so if there's if there
are contradictions
should we reconcile them if we're in a
team trying to use this
um should we just live with them and
just move forward
um or where should we actually highlight
them so this is in a way trying to think
in a um outside of maybe this sort of
laser focus
on the scientific
philosophical point and saying okay when
we're trying to bring these into a team
context
should we would we loosen some of that
so
and so just it just mentions here to
give an application should we then also
think about
active imprints being prefaced or
suffixed you know adaptive active
influence effective active influence or
active inference modeling
you know is how important is that
clarification to then
also think about how the instrumentalism
realism piece might be utilized in in
these other ways
do we need to position um
you know fully in one fully on another
and if we're in between
you know
can there be greater or lesser access to
knowing based on the context so often in
participatory work
different types of practices you know
the context is key
and then this sort of speaks a little
bit to my own idea of the co-creative
work and i know that um
you know daniel's very much with teams
and
deans very much with transformation you
know often there there's a co-creation
piece there's a there's a bit where you
you want to support the butterfly
without crushing it there's something
quite delicate there
so how can we
at times
bring this into spaces where it's it's a
co-creative space you know where there's
modeling happening in a more subtle
contextual way
and
while we have these
scientific definitions and strategic
designs and hard analysis
and they're useful we don't want them to
crush um what's happening
and there's a couple of pictures there
that
sort of speak to that and i'll pass it
over to dean maybe and you can speak to
the sampling
of waters in between and the mind the
gap
well i i think i think
that was a beautiful explanation and i
think
when if and when the authors are able to
come on that'll be something that we'll
now be able to put some color to i think
we've i think we put some anchors in the
ground but we haven't said how much
how much flow
can go between those different nodes and
that's what i think we wanted to
establish right here is the betweenness
lots of times
like it says mind the gap that's the
only thing that can kill you at the
subway
all right because you're not paying
attention to the gap and i think the
sampling of the waters in between does
the same thing except it provides a
little different
subtle difference in terms of the
fluidity of those kinds of gaps so i
think it would be really interesting if
we if we use that as our portal into how
we might bring things together and
make them
dance when they otherwise would be
sitting on chairs on the opposite side
of the room that might be an interesting
conversation to start in the dot one and
two
thank you both and the only comment i'll
add here is
this discussion we've been having on the
adjectives that preface
the adaptive affective etc active
inference
and then also stephen the focus you've
brought to the suffix that x and
brackets
active inference model as one instance
or case or realization
active inference framework active
inference process theory what what
follows and this really reminds me of
left branching and right branching
clauses in grammar and syntax
and that there's a base clause
what is our base clause and then what
branches before during and after i think
there's a very rich space and i really
like these embodied
and flux based metaphors that help us
understand um
so much so
into the paper overviews
this will just be some metadata and
descriptions on the papers before we
pull back to the background in context
and then move forward into the papers
running through their main points
so we're not going to read the abstracts
they're both
of course available for these papers
here is the abstract for active
inference and abduction
here's the abstract for inactive dynamic
social cognition and active inference
here are the keywords for both of these
papers the inactive paper
has the keywords social cognition niche
construction
active inference theory of mind and
activism and dynamical systems theory
the abduction paper has the key words
abduction active inference free energy
principle first and blanket
triadic relations and pierce
let's go to the aims of
and the claims of
the abduction paper
so
dean would you like to cover
any of the aims of the abduction paper
what i would like to do is just sort of
foretell what
both of both papers want to aim at and
that is you'll see a key word in the
second bullet of this one which is
alliance and then there are words that
you're going to see in the other paper
where they're again saying
we want things to come together
but we want to be careful on how we
describe that coming together we don't
want it to be perceived metaphorically
as a blending as an undoing of
two two or more things that we believe
have an associative
um relationship and so i think when
you're going through the aims of the two
papers if you if you kind of step back a
little bit you'll see that the authors
of both papers are are
doing a hard ex explanation on what
relationship
they want us to pay attention to and so
that's something that they both papers
share it's a heavy emphasis on
relationship
great point and they both are very
richly and powerfully written
and here we see alliance and allegiance
and certainly there's going to be a lot
of discussion in both the papers about
integrating disparate or partially
related ontologies and vocabulary sets
and different thinkers different threads
of intellectual development
these quotes from the paper can be read
and of course are expanded upon in the
paper
but as dean said this paper's focus is
on the intellectual alliance
between active inference and free energy
principle fep and primarily the work of
cs pierce
in terms of semiotics pragmatics
grammaticism abductive logic that is the
aim synthesis is bringing those two
together in a way that's synergistic and
and is providing meaning stephen
yeah and just following on from what
you're saying the both these papers and
particularly the abductive one
it gives a way to look at
areas that are really hard to
simulate for computers um and
the the way that abduction happens or
particularly with humans is
very sophisticated and i think
it's really helpful to then see
semiotics which is actually used a lot
in
theater sonography and set design
um pragmatism so brought into this with
a with a with a really
a theory that's you know transcends
science often right is often used in
other fields like
the natural sciences has some use for it
but it's often used in the humanities so
i think
this is speaking to that piece about
what is it that
is revealed that kind of secret sauce
that kind of hit in the soul which is
normally missing and in action
there's also something that's like that
awesome
claims of the paper
are throughout the paper but just to
highlight some of the key claims
they're claiming that that aim that they
set out to make
between the work of active inference and
the abduction and semiotic perspective
appears they're claiming that that is
feasible and that they're providing an
initial sketch for it
in this theoretical theoretical
integration
of the new and the old
something red something blue something
new something old
and the two frameworks the new and the
old respectively
are the modern instantiations of
neuroscience and cognitive science
represented by a free energy principle
and on the old a historically accurate
and precise interpretation of abductive
inference including the importance of
the economy of research all things that
we're going to come back to just wanted
to clarify the claims there can i just
add one yes please
real quick so theoretical integration
there i mean from what if you can think
back to when we were talking about our
aims
now the question is this is what the
authors are saying
what we're wondering is does that make
active inference both the integration
product and the integrator the process
and again i want to i want to kind of
tease back that one step because i think
that's going to happen again when we
look at the other paper
they'll use different nomenclature but
they're going to say the same thing and
again
it's it's hard to see the commonalities
unless you and you don't have to make
them up
you just have to
notice them in in
the two different types of forests
and a point on that they're
both in a way using active inference as
an integrator as well as a
differentiator we're making an
integrated model of internal and
external and blanket states
by differentiating them and then of
course integration and differentiation
also have a joint
usage in mathematics with the integral
and the derivative notation so there's
going to be a lot of things coming
together um
steven's your hands still up yes please
yeah just one thing as well i think this
is really helpful to talk about
neuroscience in this computational
neuroscience and to highlight that
because i think
something that
is the reality in the world out there
the culture out there where
where these ideas are circulating is
that neuroscience
is turned on its head basically by
active influence
neuroscience as a field
as people understand it
is
some sort of
deductive
process of stuff coming in and then
being evaluated and
concretized as opposed to this
predictive journey so i think it's
really really useful
because this is this is something that
we all face and i think what i also have
noted when i've spoken to some
neuroscientists is they've actually had
like an existential crisis and shifted
partly often by coming up with inactive
claims and seeing really if inactive
claims are there how can their work with
neuroscience be
so held together so
there's this there's there's a piece
here that relates to the general and and
that that general
piece is is more important
when we start to bring um
active influence out from
the specialist areas where it's kind of
enclaved and its rules of the game are
known and you're into the areas where
people say neuroscience well i know what
that means
and off you go so thanks great thank you
the paper has relatively few sections
it has an introduction
it then presents a
a pairing
of active inference in the light of
abduction
abduction in the light of active
inference
slightly oblique reference to nothing in
biology makes sense except in the light
of evolution or except in the light of
something and these are two lights
back to that islands what is the space
between
and then there's a discussion
on the economy of research and its free
energy naturalization and the conclusion
and the pierce rabbit holes run deep
we're going to go into a few soon
on to the inactive paper
so here we're going to be describing the
ames claims and roadmap of the inactive
dynamic social cognition and active
inference paper
the paper presents a two-fold aim
to dissect new accounts
that blend in activism with inferential
accounts and explain why doing so
involves contradiction
is the first aim
and the second aim is to offer
the only reasonable account linking in
activism and inferential accounts
especially on this case of social
cognition
so
yes please no guess what i was hoping
could you now turn the word linking
purple for us
yes
thank you
we have different ways of describing the
between that stephen did a lovely job of
of emphasizing before we actually
started looking at the um
the papers themselves
yeah it's in between yeah
it's awesome and it is actually
through your request and the slides
platform it becomes an active dynamic
social stigmargic
and so
that's a proof of concept for what
but this is the aims of this paper okay
they also have many claims
articulated throughout the discussion
and they actually use some very clear
notation to describe the specific claims
from other work and from their own work
and about which claims and hypotheses
have which logical relationship
um
they're going to make claims about the
nature of cognition and its embodied
basis
they're going to be discussing some of
the claims related to the human social
cognitive niche
and talking about the importance of
relationship enculturation niche
construction
and then they're going to be talking
about theory of mind tom
and about the compatibility or
contradictions
associated with linking
inactive
claims with
theory of mind or inferential accounts
the paper's
roadmap lays out many of these aims and
claims quite clearly they begin with an
introduction
and introduce a
recent though influential work in the
active inference field which is the
thinking through other minds framework
ttom
and they as they say dissect this
account
to try to tease apart the way that in
their view
the inactive and the inferential counts
were brought together
they also have a figure describing a
markov blanket which is going to be a
concept that plays keely in both of
their papers
section 2 something's got to give
rejecting inactive inference through
other minds
they're going to utilize two assumptions
namely that social cognition reduces to
mental representation and two that
social cognition is hardwired from birth
and they're going to disagree with both
of these assumptions and in their
opposition to these assumptions
supported by subclaims and evidence
that is going to lead them to their
broader conclusions
they're going to use dynamical systems
theory
and talk about how dst
can be linked with an activism in terms
of its compatibility and what these two
frameworks offer each other within an
instrumentalist reading
and then they're going to discuss active
inference specifically in the context of
dynamical systems theory on one hand and
inactive
cognition social cognition on the other
hand that's the inactive dynamic
hyphenation
they'll describe with a few figures
about similarities and differences
between social inaction generally as
conceptualized outside of active
inference and then they're going to
introduce visually how active inference
enriches that picture
and then they have a very interesting
table distinguishing between or amongst
phenomena observed in the natural world
and observed behavior in the natural
world
okay
awesome to run through the papers that
way
now
let us move to the background in context
section so in this section of the dot
zero
we're going to
use some quotes from the paper for sure
but we're also going to pull a step back
and demonstrate just the tip of the
iceberg of the scholarship and the
research that we carried out leading up
to this point
hopefully to excite
the listener or reader
and to provide some context into these
very deep threads that are going to be
approached and approximated in the
papers
i'll provide a first note here or dean
please go for it
just i guess i think this is a
spectacular moment to say
okay so
background and context so we're talking
maybe
the temporal and the physical
setting
so that's now something that we can
situationally analyze
and again
it doesn't matter whether you use active
inference or whether you use a cast
model or whether you use
professional initiatives programming
bottom line is everybody is trying to
figure out
what the situation is
through an analysis method and and and
i would imagine that every one of those
methods
has a greater or lesser viability
depending upon what the situation both
temporally and physically is
so i i think
that's the critical things we're not
saying that each of these papers
are good or bad
we're saying that each of these papers
has a focus on a different
background context combination minimum
of two so now if we pull the two things
together we can't say
that that it's going to be the same
thing that we're going to come up with
that our aims as people who have now
looked at the two papers side by each
that's going to create a whole new
entity
thank you
to lead off this background and
contextualizing section i wanted to
invoke one of my favorite artisan poets
william blake
and blake wrote
contraries are positives a negation is
not a contrary
negations are not contraries contraries
mutually exist
but negations exist not
exceptions and objections and unbeliefs
exist not nor shall they ever be
organized forever and ever
end quote
contraries in this blakeyan
fourfold logical framework
in fact
are part of a dialectic and they exist
as a function of each other like convex
and concave or like gravity and
radiation as buckminster fuller might
take it towards
and so negations in this poetical
framework
are those which
exist not
whereas a and b can be on the contrary
whereas a and not a have a different
logical relationship and this kind of
four-fold logical approach
to recognizing the state space and the
truth claims that multiple juxtaposed
assertions can have with
amongst each other
is also foresaged in a lot of world
knowledge traditions
um for example the kata scotty
and this is a logical
tool and method that's been applied for
a very long time in the uh the dharmic
traditions of the indian context
wanted to provide that and also um
with these images which either of you
are welcome to explore
what does one hand clapping or a person
doing the splits
have to do with contradiction and
negation
yes dean yeah
regarding contradiction as well and i
think this
points to
the the kind of the contextual piece
um
the situational
uh analysis piece
is
there's there's the situation
inside which
there's there's there's the
contradictions are constructed if that
makes sense
um and that's also embodied and enacted
through our life so it might well be
as a baby we you know
the the morphology of the child at
different
stages in different contexts gives the
ways
to
establish situational
awareness
and the contradictions within that
as things become codified so you've got
these these
these situational
um
processes are kind of um are what we're
doing in this ongoing modeling flow the
kind of the fields of practice
in these different papers that underpin
them the inactivist feels a practice or
the um the more computational fields of
practice they've they're what we kind of
embody and we get into and we learn
and that's what we're kind of
intuitively modeling in a way we get a
feel for how we should model being
in these situations the contradictions
but that modelling
often and this is the danger
when it gets
overpowered by someone with their model
i.e
someone's in their world modeling what
it's like to be themselves or trying to
process it they go and see a counsellor
with their model and that model
is being used to fit them to the model
and then that counselor will tell us
what their problem is how it's framed so
i think this model model in
um is
quite relevant here because you know
once these contradictions are
established it might well be that
there's a model created within that
domain
and then someone who's not necessarily
in that domain
can
be ascribed to the model they don't know
what the game is they're not in the
process and the model takes over so that
sort of switches over to the splits
because then okay we've got two things
they're together
we we're talking about this yes let's
you open up and you've got a stance
okay so i'm slightly and at some point
it's like that's not a stance brother
that's that's a split you've got into
there you're going to have to be careful
right so you've gone into this idea that
you're opening things up now were they
one thing to start with were they a
stance that they were held in some ways
have they split in a in in a way where
they're now
isolated from each other you know i
suppose we're trying to hopefully find a
way to neither push them into one
neither having split maybe have a stance
in between
that is um somehow agile and uh
relates in this case to realism and
instrumentalism that kind of echoes some
broader themes
thank you dean
just real quick um a lot of people have
heard the yogi baronism of when you see
a fork in the road
take it and i know that with the with a
lot of the term joint
has come up a lot joint probability for
example and so the idea of split here
is a really good one for metaphorically
speaking because
if you are
looking at something with active
interference and you are assuming that
in a tea maze experiment you have to go
left or right well human beings
can see a fork in the road and take it
that's kind of the standing joke
if you see a fork in my legs take them
don't necessarily
you have to choose a orbee you can take
the whole thing and i think that's what
blake is trying to point at with this
exercise and so is that a contradiction
no if i see utensil on the road i can
take it but if i'm not open
to the idea that fork doesn't only mean
left or right
then i'm already self-limited in terms
of what i am testing what i'm
situationally analyzed
thank you both all right into the more
direct keyword pieces
so in action from thisdefinitions.net
site an action is one of the possible
ways of organizing knowledge and the
forms of interaction with the world
inactive knowledge is knowledge that
comes through action and is constructed
on motor skills such as manipulating
objects riding a bicycle or playing a
sport that's just one of many
definitions that have been provided
we've also had several live streams and
paper discussions on an action in active
inference
for example
in active live stream number six
way back when in 2020 we discussed
ramstead at all a tale of two densities
active inference is an active inference
in
2021 we discussed a paper also of
hippolyto at all embodied skillful
performance where the action is
and interestingly
for saging in some ways this very
discussion here's a slide from
that live stream um
with uh of the hippolyto paper
and here we had the piercing
uh triad and we had the symbolism and
this the semiotics and the references to
french
so we actually were talking about the
very related concept of representation
and indeed those who support
and or reject and or find contradiction
and linkage all of the above
the discussion around
inactivism and the inferential account
is going to hinge very much on the
question of representation and cognitive
representations what those are where or
if they exist and so on
um that was livestream 23.
also from this paper of sangati at all
uh they lay out just visually we're
gonna see more representations soon
in their view
some of the distinctions between
traditional social cognition
and inactive social cognition
and so rather than just a visual
interpretation of the image name deem
would you like to provide it
no i i wait to you down in the next okay
so here here what i see is that in the
traditional social cognitive inferential
accounts
the gears are turning inside the brain
and then there's perception action loops
and linkages that connect social
entities that are in their body but the
body is seen as like an interface
for that kind of information transfer
one extreme stance or simple visual
representation
and then here in contrast we see like
the gears are everywhere including in
the environment in the niche in the
space between
and that yes the brain is doing things
but also it's part of an enacted system
that is implementing this encultured
social cognitive process a little bit
more in a holistic framing so dean yes
yeah i was just going to say
in a minute we're going to look at what
the abduction thing talks about but for
now
i would like people just to sort of hold
in their mind the idea that
this is speaking to a type of temporal
depth but that temporal depth is
vertical
i think abduction looking at longer
timelines for hundreds of years is more
horizontal so just keep in mind that
we're talking temporal depth but the
focus is on a vertical or a deep
temporal depth instead of a wide lateral
temporal depth
they both matter but they're orthogonal
doesn't mean that they're in conflict
with one another it just means they're
going in different directions that's all
i want to say about that
it's funny left and right or west and
east those are contrary directions but
they're not negatory directions and so
right there is where we start to see
like how orthogonality or sparsity
or conditional independence
granted by a markov blanket for example
how those can be seen in the framework
of contraries though not negations
stephen
and that gear in the in the right hand
diagram there the the gear in between
you know that can have temporal depth
that can have this mind-body environment
piece is definitely there like you're
saying and obviously makes as a unit of
analysis that's really challenging and i
would also put in there as a gear words
words are
twitch
twitching of our voice box is giving us
words in space around us
so you know they're being used as tools
as well so suddenly
we're much more enmeshed even if it's
just speech
yeah and it takes time for the speech to
travel through the internet and through
space and time
a little bit more depth on social
inaction
this uh inaction research resource
describes several meanings and senses of
inaction
in the performative and the bringing
forth senses so please read
and also a really nice 2009 paper in
cognitive semiotics by de bruyne and de
haan
discuss some of the relationships of an
activism in social cognition
and they did an excellent job of
summarizing what the inferential
and the inactivist accounts can bring
together and sort of
discuss that linkage yes please dean
yeah i
read that people because i found it and
here's an interesting thing if they're
going to use a bridge metaphor
i think an activism does have a bridge
it's just a vertical bridge
it's the side of a building going up
and so
um
nothing not in not to criticize what
they've written here but i think there
is a debt
and there is an ability to span it's
just that it's going
vertical it's not going traditionally
side to side
awesome
so on to a little bit of depth into
abduction and semiotics
well
we had quite the learning journey
together
and the
abduction paper
with
one or one and a half or even two of the
authors being true pearson experts
provided many details
pierce was a prolific writer and thinker
and collaborator and also much of the
work was unpublished which means that
there are some arcane reference systems
and not all of it is hyper accessible
we found the commons.org site to be
immensely useful in providing many
definitions as well as links to
resources dean would you like to
summarize anything on this page
nothing other than if you if you
if you are interested in
pragmatism and you want to get past
william james actually william james and
charles sanders pierce had a bit of a
they were they were maybe 150 years ago
the first
conflictors around how things work
um it's actually really it's an amazing
takeoff point in terms of how people who
appear to be in competition with one
another actually make one another
smarter but in fact a lot of the things
a lot of the ideas that we 150 years
later are now looking back on we would
have to say they may felt they were in
competition with one another but i think
what they were doing was relaying or
somehow building a better model because
they weren't always looking at things as
through the same eyes they had both eyes
open so that's i'll just say go go to
the common site it's it's really good
yeah it's great this representation
ironically slash
appropriately is of the well-known
pearson triad semiotic framework where a
stop sign is called the representamen
the represented
instance the physical stop sign the real
stop sign
the object is the message cars must stop
here and the interpretant is i should
stop here and that's where we get that
entity agency
i found a interesting paper
about the user interface
which brings some of these truly
timeless discussions on semiotics and
logic into a digital context
they're applying that semiosis to the
user interface metaphor
one could imagine if that were a stop
sign in the real world or if it were a
button on a website in a user interface
context
and
anyone may pause and read some of these
very excellent selections from quotes
and uh
lectures given
on how
copies signs and symbols are linked
through logic and semiosis
a lot here but we'll carry on
to abduction specifically so this was a
little bit on pierce and the definition
of semiotics as opposed to
the science of things the more positive
sciences and the science of forms which
are the more formal sciences
what is abductive reasoning
this was very fascinating to explore
this is a quote from the abduction paper
they wrote it is common in the secondary
literature
eg that building on pierce
to conceive abduction as occurring in
two parts or two kinds
generative abduction and selective
abduction
here's another perspective on the two
types or the two varietals or two
components two-stroke engine of
abduction from the stanford encyclopedia
uh philosophy
they wrote in the philosophical
literature the term abduction is used in
two related but different senses
in both senses the term refers to
explanatory reasoning
in the historically first sense it
refers
to the place of explanatory reasoning in
generating hypotheses that's generative
abduction while in the second sense
which is the sense which it is used most
frequently in the modern literature it
refers to the place of explanatory
reasoning in justifying or evaluating an
enumerated set of hypotheses
and in a sense it makes it makes sense
the content has to be generated to be
curated the ideas have to be specified
enumerated in order to be justified or
evaluated
dean please continue on this
well just just real quickly so
we now have red and blue which was
really really important to highlight
that you need both you need a minimum of
two for the explanation to
appear
next abductive reasoning in the
probabilistic sense is also known as
inference to the best explanation is a
form of logical reasoning that looks to
the most likely hypothesis to explain
something an example did the white beans
in the left hand come from the bag of
objects held in the right hand here we
can see how the hypothesis put forward
depends on
an incomplete observation or an
inference are there beans also in the
bag and even if so is that the source
for what has been transferred to the
left hand so again temporal depth
when you arrive into a situation
what what kind of background and what
kind of context do you possess
is going to go to this this fourth form
of logic that or purse look literally
spent a lifetime
trying to
disentangle and then
reform into some sort of coherence
and
those listening along may start to see
inklings of priors sensory observations
posterior updating of beliefs about the
world even action selection coming into
play especially translation of the
affordances instantaneous action
availabilities into policies which can
be evaluated by their expected free
energy but we're going to get there
let's turn
to abduction and here are some of the
very fascinating papers available on
commons related to abduction a lot there
and to kind of continue on with one of
the resources from commons on
abduction as practical inference
by thomas capitan
this work
which we're not going to read everything
about goes into a lot of interesting
points
about that dual nature of abduction
with hypothesis generating
and hypothesis selection
and distinguishes that hypothesis
selection
can make deductively valid evaluations
however the creativity phase is
non-inferential that has a lot of
resonance with like not pre-censoring
ideas and having like an inclusive
discussion when brainstorming
and recognizing that there has to be a
winnowing in a finite period of space
and time
additionally there's some discussion
here
this was
relating
as we move back towards or interweave
with free energy principle
initial awareness of the hypothesis
comes with the observation of a
collogated whole by means of an
uncontrolled insight into the world of
ideas into what he called thirdness as
given in perception
the novel conceiving of any instance of
premise 2
citing a previous part of paper is
caused by prior cognitions
priors
its content is suggested by the facts
observations sensory observations
but not everything suggested is inferred
from the cognition of the facts
and so
pierce goes on to describe there are
operations of the mind which are
logically exactly analogous to
inferences
accepting only that they are unconscious
and therefore uncontrollable and
therefore not subject to criticism so
leaving aside questions like whether
unconscious processes could be
considered controllable
here we very much see hints of
perception as unconscious inference and
we see also continuity
between processes of attention and
awareness
conscious inferences
and other subconscious inferences and so
in a way this is also providing an
integrated framework of perception
learning belief updating temporal depth
conscious and unconscious awareness all
of these features are explored in the
persian work and the abduction
paper is going to very specifically
highlight that fact
okay carrying on a little bit more
uh abduction and retroduction
would you like to add anything on this
one dean
well i mean people that studied it and
analyzed this
wonder at times whether or not this was
a
morphology or whether or not we can use
the two terms simultaneously or
interchangeably
again it's probably one of those things
where if you
want to find out what the details are
you should probably go and have a look
because it's interesting but it doesn't
at this point all we basically want to
do is
here i'll just read this
retroduction of the process whereby from
the surprising array of facts we are led
to a
conjectural we've used conjecture a lot
theory to account for them many
logicians refuse to call this last
inference
because its conclusion is so extremely
problematical as to amount a little more
than an interrogation
i'm sure they are wrong however they
have not possessed
themselves of the true scientific
definition of inference so what he's
basically saying here is let's not
call
abductive reasoning infrared um
inductive reasoning
the logical justification of a
retroduction of which the proper
conclusion is that the conjectured state
of things is likely
in the vague sense of tending
to resemble the real
state of things and i this is the part
where so what replaces that
instrumentalism
whatever whatever we define as
this is again
this is one of those conundrums if it's
not if it's not
real
state is it what isn't then what is an
unreal or a non-real state because it's
there
we've labeled it
what what fills that what feels that
eventually to make the whole that's the
question here
and also again worthwhile reading some
of the prior work of one of the authors
of the abduction paper and one can see
in their research a strong line of
developing and extending and modernizing
a lot of the work
let's just
yeah so i put down those uh bear signs
because i want to tell a really really
really quick story
so if you live somewhere where there are
bears if the bear sign stays up
people begin to ignore the actual
sign
object
and they no longer become interpreters
they they willfully
lose that triadic so
if you're in the business of
of animal
welfare and you don't want bears to
become too
used to human contact you have to be
very selective when you put the sign up
and most importantly when you remove the
sign
so i wanted to put that up there because
that's a big part of the abductive and
retroduction piece it's
you have to sometimes take things away
for abduction to work it's the removal
of possibilities
that actually
creates an emphasis
i think we'll just carry on to realism
and instrumentalism because we're going
to come back to abduction in the
subsequent discussions more so
here are some quotes from a fair bend
paper
according to realism such knowledge
factual knowledge is descriptive of
general or particular features of the
universe so that doesn't mean that the
model of gravity is gravity doesn't mean
that the model of gravity is what the
objects of gravity are
but a realist would remark that for
example formal models of gravity teach
us of the existence of
objects acted upon by the force gravity
and license the description of a force
which cannot be directly seen heard or
felt but still has noticeable
influence
forces are real things are real
according to instrumentalism
even a theory that is wholly correct
does not describe anything but serves as
an instrument for the prediction of the
facts that constitute its empirical
content
and so again on this newton's
gravitation example the instrumentalists
could take the position there are no
entities
gravitation force and gravitational
fields
are merely instrumental applications
of statistical
arguments or potentially even social or
power dynamical arguments
and an instrumentalist may deny the
existence of objects
entities and forces in this case
and even take things to the level of
having skepticism around words as
instruments and the relationships around
communication
and how it orders and predicts sense
data
we've explored realism and
instrumentalism quite a lot over the
streams and we highlighted a lot in mel
andrews work in live stream number 14.
one more slide on realism and
instrumentalism and then either of you
please feel free
um
i'll describe some of the bottom ones
again the map territory distinction is
very
key to the realism and instrumentalism
conversation
there's also been variety of excellent
philosophical work
for example a successor to the realism
anti-realism question
those two by the way i would say are
negations whereas realism and
instrumentalism
we are suggesting might be seen as
contraries
and also helen longano's work on
scientific pluralism has a lot to say
about this by taking a
multi-disciplinary lens on realism and
instrumentalism
and then dean would you like to describe
anything about this top paper you found
uh
i could i don't remember this in the
grand schemes to be honest it's here for
people to read there were many papers
and again we're just putting a lot of
text up for those who want to pause and
follow the trails
and it all kind of gets enmeshed in
stephen any comments on realism
instrumentalism
i suppose the piece that i
comes to mind for me a lot is
all of this is then underpinned
within action at some level so
the the
the idea of looking for
um different
contradictions or different um
retro
approaches
could be a case of you imagine
when someone thinks about taking a path
through the woods
you know or you could re-embody a lot of
these things
or and maybe everything at some level is
is goes through some embodiment
um and when it's conceptual that
embodiment is just happening in a more
conceptual space
um that doesn't rely on as many other
um
kind of stories or
feeling your way through things
so um
the difference that happens when you're
in a field of practice is that you're so
used to being in that field of practice
that
that embodiment becomes the water that
you swim in
so that could be
something that sort of relates to this
great yes dean just real quick so
again we'll ask at this point yes to
realism
yes to instrumentalism
yes to the end
not or
undone
we had a little ampersand here and we
the and here
um one brief note on for e cognition
we won't go into depth here but 4e can
refer to as per the xiavio and van der
schiff 2018 paper which was in the
context of music pedagogy which is a
very fascinating area 4e is embodied
embedded embedded
extended enacted
encultured etc etc etc 7e 11e 22e all of
them and then a fun quote from carl
fristen
from our
applied active inference symposium in
he said one key thing about active
inference
is it's it's beyond predictive
processing it's beyond sentience and it
emphasizes or reflects the pragmatic
turn at the beginning of this century
really epitomized by the four e's
to make it clear that sentience is
active
and that you are talking about
the circular causality of engagement
with any particle personal or plant with
whatever's out there purple circular
causality and all of that entails
then quite briefly we're not going to go
into any of these details but here's a
bunch of work that's relevant for the
inactive paper
just some of the other background
citations and other work that one might
want to look into
and for the abductive paper
and also a little bit of leaning even
into something hopefully the authors can
unpack for us on the the role and
relationship of nominalism with all of
this but many previous papers by the
authors here
listed and a lot of great work again so
thanks you fellows for
this journey
now
we can enter into the two papers or the
space between
let's have an initial juxtaposition of
the two papers i'll put our video will
be the tip of the iceberg here so dean
you're the tip of the iceberg what would
you like to say about these two papers
in an initial juxtaposition
well as i said i think
if you actually step back and realize
that what people are doing by
by pairing to active inference
you are saying
i have i have a a particular kind of
situational analysis that i would like
to perform and in doing so i would like
to try to remove contradictions or i
would like to
formulate integrations
and if you step back to that place
your
your example of so your your hyper your
hyper um
your head your subject is is sub uh
situational analysis your example
fitting under that
you're not now making
the mistake of saying
my way of do it looking at things
automatically negates or turns other
ways of looking at everything that's
under that title a situation situational
analysis to dust now
there are comparisons and they're not
written here and they're so ready along
i just basically chose examples within
each of the papers where
papers are talking about two different
focal points but they're still within
this larger larger
marginal
boundary of active inference and how
active inference
is behaving
around the behavior
within a regime of attention and opening
that up to something more available than
the specifics or the scale friendly
thing of does theory of mind necessarily
blend
with active inference or
does the idea that abduction the moment
when i arrive actually
negate any possibility of using
instruments to extend my my sensory
window
right so again we're not going to spend
a whole lot of time
pulling those other things out but if
people want to actually see how when you
set approximately two papers beside one
another you can find a ton of
similarities
it's kind of an interesting exercise it
takes a while
but when you actually see them side by
each and entangled there's a there's a
lot of braiding going on
thank you dean stephen
yeah i like this um
like dean was talking about there you've
got these two papers it could almost be
seen as two icebergs where
their their philosophies are kind of
frozen and
given shape and form and there is stuff
underneath and stuff above
but there's also the water around in
between
which may have
lots of uh shrimp and all sorts of
things swimming around so
i think in this this list here where
you've kind of got realism
instrumentalism well they're your two
icebergs right
we want them to be nice and sharp
and maybe you get knocked a bit if you
bang off them and then okay statistics
and model comparison
you know
they they they're still out there but
they might jive a little bit multi-agent
belief communication oh hold on we've
got something flowing here
things as assembled ensembles sorry
models as ensembles
perspective
or tights perspective or where are those
perspectives coming from ways of knowing
stochasticity complex systems
and so forth
um
we're now maybe
i don't know if we're not dissolving the
the iceberg that's not about that the
iceberg's there but we're they're
different types of um
ways and
of starting to maybe be more flexible
and less stable
awesome so into the inactive paper we go
so to keep things reasonable and also
have a lot to discuss in the one and two
again we put a lot of content onto the
slides for your pausing and enjoying
most of the content is copied and quoted
from the paper so that is the point of
reference to learn more
we'll just walk through
in the order of the roadmap some of the
key
pieces that the papers go through so
in section one of the inactive paper
they're going to begin with a
summarization
of vessier at all's 2020 argument for
understanding others in the world and
that's presented in this thinking
through other minds ttom paper and then
tom is theory of mind
they summarize
or capture the argument of thinking
through other minds as one
premise one social cognition is inactive
and embodied two inactive and embodied
the social actor cannot directly grasp
social cognition
three anything that cannot be directly
grasped must be inferred
ergo qed conclusion inactive and
embodied social cognition must be
inferred there must be inference about
social cognition
and the authors of the inactive paper
state that by premise two and three
ttom joins the tom orthodoxy
understanding the world and others to
them comes down to the ability to infer
and attribute mental states
that is the uh summarization of thinking
through other minds
and they are going to call into question
on this critical dissection that such a
ttom account is indeed making this happy
marriage with an activism
they're going to pull on yes any anyone
or continue okay they're gonna they're
gonna they're gonna pull out on a few
different of these premises
and what hidden assumptions might be
underlying those premises like what
axioms lead one to generate such
premises
the contradiction between p1 and p2
results from two hidden assumptions in
that t2m argument so here we see p123
above
and then hidden assumption one
social cognition reduces to information
in explicit propositional form
mental representation and ascription
they are going to say this they are
feeling this way as a mental
representation
and hidden assumption too social
cognition is hardwired with the concepts
and logical tools for inference for
example
at birth
and in the subsequent sections
they're going to analyze and clarify the
contradiction between premises one and
two
this tension of
if social cognition isn't active and
embodied
is it really the case or is it a
contradictory claim
that social cognition cannot be directly
grasped by such a social actor
they're then going to critically assess
from the inactive perspective what
problems might underlie these
assumptions the hidden assumptions and
why an activist reject these hidden
assumptions
and hence reject the premises listed
above
and then they're going to be exploring
what are these non-representational
methods and mechanisms of
co-construction in social action
they have a markov blanket
a representation visually that we've
seen here before
with the internal states external states
and the mediation of internal and
external states by blanket states
which as per the pearl 1988 definition
are the blanket states making the
internal and external states
conditionally independent
sometimes people go further and describe
a fristen blanket where the blanket
states b
are partitioned into two kinds of states
sense and active
and those two kinds of states are
defined by their incoming from the
perspective of internal states
statistical dependencies sensory states
and outgoing statistical dependencies
which can be interpreted as actions or
interfaces from
the entity or thing towards the niche
but we'll come back to markov blankets
and more later
yes stephen go for it
just coming back to that
actually the page the slide before this
but relating to this is when it says
things cannot be directly there's a
couple of things that directly be
grasped well i would argue that with
that that's a useful distinction because
when we think about um we're talking
about the grip and the grip or a pair of
pliers and i can't directly grip a hot
pipe i need the pliers i can't directly
um do a number of things without maybe
more than one tool
but there's a sense that
when we talk about grasping things or
when people are thinking about if
something is
you know to grasp something
that is explicitly propositional
you know we have other kinds of tools
that might be coming to play even when
we think about words
and the act of ascribing
all of these things can be
performances with tools at every level
so there's a
there's an interesting blending going on
here depending on how
the iceberg gets melted
great
in section two one
which you can read in the paper or pause
here and capture many aspects of it
they're going to question the assumption
that social cognition reduces to mental
representation
and
their point can be distilled as
understanding others is a matter of
being skilled at shared non-explicit
meanings
and potentially some
abductive
ding-ding-ding and model-based reasoning
all of which are context-specific
modifiable and dynamic
and they are going to unpack in the
further paragraphs that in there in lies
an evident contradiction between those
first two premises which is really like
the achilles heel or the soft spot where
they're gonna be targeting their logic
in section two
they're going to question that second of
the assumptions which is that social
cognition is hardwired from birth
and so while they do qualify the ttom
position
and they say vessier do not hold a
nativist position for example like a
pure inborn perspective
because they do have a focus on the
developmental and ecological dynamics of
how culture is acquired
they do call into question the
acquisition of the starter pack
and they're also exploring more in this
section some inactivist critiques of for
example hardwired perspectives on social
cognition
in section 3
having critiqued assumptions that in
their mind highlight the contradiction
inherent within thinking through other
minds they're going to suggest another
relationship oh you don't like that dish
let's try this one
and this is going to be a
approach from dynamical systems theory
or dst they write
dst
as we shall argue in this section is an
approach that serves to learn about and
generate predictive power about the
socioculturally situated practices of
agents constructing their niche
because dst has at its core
useful tools such as emergence
non-linearity and spontaneity etc
it allows us to move away from
prefabricated notions of tom theory of
mind-like theories of social cognition
one should therefore refrain from making
ontological assumptions
ontological here being about how things
are in the world
so more of the philosophers ontology
rather than the computer science
knowledge management sense of ontology
one should refrain from making these
kinds of ontological assumptions
licensed by realism
about the complex system based upon a
tractable model
so just because the model is so
tractable
doesn't mean that we have the license
to make ontological assumptions
since the tractable model is an
opportunity for learning about the
complex behavior only epistemic claims
are allowed
let us take a closer look at the claim
to make it tractable we can represent a
dynamical system by a static
relationship as follows and here are
their equations one two and three with
the captions below
and they're using these very
simple kind of like the kernel of the
dynamical systems theory is
understanding how
things are a function of how they change
broadly and it's represented in a few
different ways
in terms of a successor model and more
of a ray of change model
stephen
i think this is a very
useful point point number three there
the bullet point because it also speaks
to that sense of
this is a modelling approach
let's see what the model in
is telling us rather than a model
fitting
approach
um which is often you know what ends up
happening if you have the defined
ontology
you know you effectively
so many things so
um
that's maybe a key
piece
that links
a lot of how things can be bridged in
terms of active inference and how it
could be held between
you know
that that is a
is a stance in a way
it's it's holding the legs apart and
saying
okay
am i doing the splits or have i got my
legs together
right so
let's find out rather than
you t someone expert tell me
um
and
yeah thanks
thank you dean yes
yeah i just wanted to add to what
stephen was just saying i
up to this point i really and i i love
the paper
that it's the constructivist piece
though that i think
has me
pausing for a minute because i believe
that in order for
us to be able to
make that decision
is it the splits or is it a fork is it
literally a fork and instead of having
to go left to right that requires a
deconstruction
that i think is oftentimes left out
prior to a reconstruction
so again i'm not arguing with the
authors because i think they're
respecting the autonomy
and i think they've done a brilliant job
of saying okay this logic this deductive
path that other authors have taken
may not necessarily apply here because
it causes too much blending so good good
good you you're you're holding up what
actually is left and right
but you're leaving out the add
the and part is it could be a fork that
i could literally pick up and the only
way you can see that is if you can
deconstruct
before you reconstruct and deconstruct
doesn't mean differentiate that's
already present deconstruct literally
means as
the oneness
when did i arrive in this moment what
have i what what parts of the puzzle am
i still missing because i'm
in in a hurry to figure out if i'm
supposed to go left or right next
especially in total context especially
there
yes stephen if you would like to give a
quick point here thanks just adding to
that um
that piece of the situationalness
um i
believe that's where you come into the
awareness of what's going on so science
is very much telling us what's going on
what is that thing what is
this what is that
but that fork in the road or being you
know a team team age junction or
something else
ultimately there's awareness piece
where is that situated and in active
inference that's often more
complex nebulous
with the scientific being about the
accuracy
of the method well
other times the awareness and the
complexity comes in active inference can
have both of those yeah great continuing
on through the latter parts of the paper
they talk a lot about complexity which
many of us love
so complexity complexity science
complexity theory brings so many
great
terms concepts people methods tools
ideas everything
and they talk a lot about autopolicies
and this recursiveness so there's a lot
of really creative linkage linkages made
in the inactive paper and complexity is
used in a really valuable way
in section four
they're going to move into active
inference in an inactive dynamic setting
and that is where active inference is
going to be deployed as an insightful
instrument to learn about and understand
the dynamics underlying cultural
co-constructions
considering it does not necessarily take
agents as passive
agents together are the authors of the
states of one another
and so
kind of analogous to the inactive
figures shown earlier where we had the
gears in the head
and then that went to like the gears
being more distributed in the body and
in the mind
here in figure 2 there's more of a
classical
meaning and model based reasoning where
different social actors are kind of
having this inferential account that is
very like one directional as shown here
with an arrow pointing just to the
middle and in figure 3 they're depicting
the social action in figure 2 under
active inference in terms of labeling
here
the internal states of the social actor
and the external states being social
actor one so this is from the
perspective of social actor two
where the blanket states are being
framed as sociocultural meaning and that
model based reasoning
which opens up for inferential accounts
that are distributed
and enacted
and
[Music]
hopefully we'll go into more detail
because this is where they are
supporting their positive
instrumentalist application of active
inference into the social inactive space
and then they write characterizing a
social scene as analogous to scientific
practice
is there by a mischaracterization it's
almost like taking what happens in the
laboratory in a certain context and even
a certain view on what happens in the
laboratory in a certain context
comma in a certain context
and then critiquing that
and thinking a bit more expansively
about what happens in the hallways of
the laboratory and in the basement and
in the world around the building
and that is also really nicely connected
to some yellow bronberg at all's work on
the anticipating brain is not a
scientist which also focuses on the
inactive perspective from an ecological
perspective not only necessarily the
social but the social is an important
case
in table 1
they're going to discuss a little bit
more about
some of the dividers and contents of
cells related to the natural world and
scientific tools and constructs
for sure we're going to return here in
subsequent discussions so just check out
table one
see what you think
what other lines would you draw would
they be kind of like curved lines like
look like letters would you circle
anything would you draw some triangles
would you add another row would you make
it a tensor what else would you draw on
table one
even if only another double bounding
line to emphasize that it's perfect as
is dean
all i would say is if you do go and have
a look at this ask yourself why these
hyper parameters and why
these laterals
because i think that will
that will lead to all kinds of
well for me it just got me so twisted
around
fun
okay and then conclusion before we move
to the second paper
we have shown that holding both an
activism and theory of mind entails
contradiction and confusion
this is evident when we critically
dissect the two hidden assumptions held
by tom like theories such as ttom which
are rejected by inactivism those two
covert assumptions that they believe
disrepute the linkage
and then
they reiterate the co-constructive
nature and the embedded and ecological
components of social inaction
and the recursion and the unfolding
through time the rolling out of social
inaction
and they suggest that dynamical systems
theory
and active inference instrumentally
applied as a type of dynamical systems
modeling
has promise
and is a suitable and complementary tool
to consider social understanding as
generalized synchronization
held in a certain way
so that was that paper and
it will now be paired
with the abductive paper so
one breath before we move into abduction
yes stephen
taking that breath um that last sentence
there about how it can be
um almost a bridge they're the the
complementary um
use of dynamical systems theory
and sort of fills a gap they're sort of
filling the gap and in a way i think as
we talk about the abduction paper some
of the gaps that doesn't fill
i know we're not trying to talk about
filling gaps here but let's say you're
filling gaps
abduction
might also feel so you know the
the beauty of the beauty of active
inference and the bayesian approach is
that lots of different
scales and modalities and can be
weighted and blended to give you
um potentially a feel
for what to do right so
it doesn't mean one excludes the other
awesome
okay
inter abduction
we obtuse away
the paper begins with a relatively
short and very concise
introduction to some of the key points
of the paper
we described earlier in their aims that
they're interested in this naturalistic
rendering
of some of cs pierce's later
eg post 1903 or post 1905
mostly unpublished work
unpacking the semiotic and logical
notions of abductive reasoning which we
covered in the context section
they're aiming for this biological model
of abduction
which is going to
thread the needle
weave the fabric whatever it is
that maintains the functional integrity
of the organism
the evolutionary imperative for that
living being's existence and to be
compatible with modern neuroscience
they focus on the allegiance and the
alliance which we talked about earlier
and they'll introduce also in the
introduction the markov blanket concept
which will be a great point of
juxtaposition to add a little bit more
detail like if it is a front a contact
front with active inference with social
inaction and abduction
then these are like hot points or points
of contact within the interface front to
really zoom in okay how is internal
state being used in these two models and
that's where the active inference
ontology is of immense value because
even when people are speaking in
different languages or we have a
computer program an equation a poem and
then a scientific paper
when we can link and proactively use or
proactively annotate with the active
inference ontology
we gain the ability to not just say well
we're both pointing at the moon
is your finger my finger or are we
pointing at the same finger because it's
so far away and so maybe it's a little
bit off and your your ray is missing the
moon from my point of view
and so on instead we can actually get
down and not
bleed out on the operating table
but rather pin down transiently and find
a attractor that helps us really go into
that intersection rather than merely
hitting and running with just points of
resonance dean
yeah again
i'll just summarize that by saying we
can situationally analyze better because
we now actually have
a way of being able to hold some some
common
thing together
so that's all i want to add to what you
just said
and just adding one on to that as well
is yeah sorry but um
and where there may be
a difference so
you know like
there could be this understanding of a
lot of the terms the ontological
understanding and say
what often is a problem is if there's
something that's not
aligned but is
just not noticed or is brushed over say
okay this is different okay there's an
ontological change here
there's a way there's there's there's a
way for that to be tractably
like we have with active inference it's
a tractable way to do it because
otherwise there's so many ontological
things floating around in this space
which is its beauty
that it's it's not cognitively possible
to find what you need to look at
thank you
the next section
again with these two lights
co-illuminating co-constructing
no two lights can physically overlap so
there must be parallax induced by these
two lights and shadows and all kinds of
effects and maybe it's not the same
wavelength and maybe you're walking
around and different sides have
different illuminations
the section is on active inference in
the light of abduction
this
is very
fascinating section
because they're going to take that
almost
quasi-algorithmic
but certainly
pre-computational
framework
being developed in the latter 1800s
and early 1900s
and start to
interface and see
how it relates to active inference
so we can highlight more and we'll look
forward to discussing in further
sections so do pause it if you want to
read all of this or read the paper
but they're focusing on the late schema
yes please dean all i was going to say
is it's mood lighting if you actually
look down at the bottom bullet the
lighting is actually trying
purse talked about it maybe maybe i
don't know if he actually did have the
formalisms to back that up
but active inference actually does now
talk about the kind of
level of energy
that we can now maybe
see within the the two
constraints that that that that idea of
um
parameterizing back to the vice grip
sort of thing
thank you so just a few quotes that are
really fascinating here
so
in science abduction can be likened to
the logic of discovery of hypotheses
which as we discussed earlier has a
generative creative element and then a
secondary selective component like
bayesian model selection bayesian model
reduction
and they even add with a cautionary
remark that no full
assimilation of pearson abduction can
occur to ibe that's inference to the
best explanation which is one half of
the two-stroke engine and commonly
people will use abduction to refer to
probabilistic reasoning from a given set
like abduction elsewhere in the writings
this later schema
those ones that are after 1903
but
according to experts have been the least
research ones
there's beginning with an observation of
surprising factor events
observation surprise
and through a conditional major premise
concludes in a co-hortative mood again a
mood
which piers termed the investigant
it's like it has and right in it
and that is that something of imperative
importance ought to be done
pragmatism inaction policy selection
initially aroused by curiosity
uncertainty reduction entropy
that leads to the formulation of a
question
which is semantic
and
there's more discussion of the
investigand mood and other moods
yes dean one other quick thing
cohorted or co-constructed from the
other paper again
share a common prefix that we
again i think will maybe be able to
tease
some more of that
the importance of that in the next few
livestreams
awesome
they're going to continue with this
question of the economy of research
so
they formed three argumentative course
really specified areas of contact with
active inference and abduction that
they're suggesting form an initial trio
or triad
that will start to form the allegiance
between active and abductive inference
first the presence of
non-degeneratively triadic relations
then the utilization of the leading
principles of abductive reasoning
b and third the subjunctive conditional
formulation
there are some logical technicalities
thrown around but
that's what the streams are for
in point a
which you can pause and read the text of
they're going to highlight the markov
blanket concept
or rather
their realist
interpretation as frist and blankets
and
argue
that
the markov blankets again implemented in
a realist first and blanket sense
have a markedly piercing
irreducibly triadic form
focusing on the boundary as mediator
between external internal states and
therefore the thirdness arising in
semiosis
there's a lot more to say but if either
of you want to give one more point on a
okay in b
they're going to continue on by talking
about some of the guiding principles of
inference
and specifically discuss abduction's
role in guiding inference
what is the leading principle of active
inferences then
here they're going to describe some
technical details of active inference in
terms of free energy variational or
expected as bounding surprise
and then they'll connect that to some of
the primary sources of pierce and
discussions of biosemiotics which have
also been connected in a lot of
discussions that we've had on
representation and meaning and so on
and
it goes even further or deeper afield
with discussions of
synechism
as well as this
question of universal mind which is
force aging in some ways the universal
cognition pan cognitive dynamics
distributed cognitive systems
matter is effete mind by von schiller
and then they're going to argue about
pristine blankets and their construction
in terms of triadic relationships
pearson triad sign object interpret ant
leads to unexplored semantic
possibilities
bringing together some of these broader
qualitative threads in semiotic analysis
with potentially dynamical systems
theory quantitative bayesian methods and
everything else that active inference
brings along with the toolkits to
implement
and see
they're also in c going to unpack some
extremely
interesting though nuanced logical
constructive elements
of
the semiotic proposition
if i could call it that
go into it more
in further discussions
but they're going to explore
how different
framings of logical relationships
amongst clauses or assertions and
warrants and all this rhetoric
relate to
realism
abduction
and
pierce's version of realism as the
possible is what can become actual
yes there are things that are possible
but cannot become actual and then what
do we use for that adjacent or
realizable
possible
and
where might we want to use it and what's
going to break that symmetry where is
pragmatism well what would be useful to
consider would be the space of all
possibles that could happen and none
other and not be surprised by adjacent
possibles that we didn't consider but
did happen
and then maybe it's not so bad to spend
a little bit of extra thought or a few
extra computer resources on considering
possibilities that couldn't happen
but we wouldn't want to get lost in the
potentially exponential space of
possibilities that can't happen
and end up losing our focus and
attention on possibilities that can
happen which are what pierce describes
as real possibilities
and the pragmatist stance
and mood
also closes the loop with policy
selection and pragmatism in active
inference
where they say that the pragmatist
meaning of beliefs in the bane paris
formulation
is that upon one that upon which one is
capable of acting
and there's a lot of resonances there
stephen
yeah i think this also speaks then to
the need to have
we talk about scale friendly or levels
or
you know some sort of structure that
enables
this to be present because
you know active influence can sort of go
all the way down and brought in down to
the cellular level as there's ways of
looking at it
here there's a sense that okay we're
looking at
these um
ideas of um a signifier
but we know with active inference it's
not that it believes that we have
signals coming in which get processed
and aggregated
so there's there's a sort of a scale at
which you have the structures that you
have the
morphogenesis maybe to get to
a scale to make
the stop sign make sense
to be
interpreted
um as its own
signifier so i think that may be where
there's this um tension going to happen
between the inactivists here and and
where that can happen but the argument
could well i would say is that certain
scales
certain structures
and maybe certain realist
ways of things happening
something like that
is feasible
great just dean and then we'll quickly
move through the rest let me just be
real quick here i think especially in b
and and until lesser extent and c
the
the business of how we take piercings
piercing
thinking
into the active inference realm
is built on an assumption and that is
that the continue our our continuing
existence our continuing
reality um
means that we're accumulating more
experiences with the tools
in the world the rules in the world and
the pools and by pools i mean those
aggregations that stephen was just
pointing to thank you for bringing that
up steven because that made me want to
write this down aggregations as
densities
tale of two densities materializing
so again i don't know
that you
exclusively say everything is real and
then all the examples underneath it are
also real because even pierce himself
said that there is an aspect of this
reality which we will never
be able to describe as anything other
than
non-reality
even though we're fundamentally using it
so how does that
how does that
enable these densities to form and i
know that sounds way the heck and gone
out there
i'm sorry but it's actually something we
have to contemplate
thanks
they're then going to
flip the script or at least the syntax
and talk about abduction in the light of
active inference
here is where they kick off with that
acknowledgement of the two-stroke engine
with generative abduction and selective
abduction
and then they're going to connect that
to some of the ontology of active
inference in terms of like seeing
selective abduction
as a sampling
process
and understanding where generative
abduction fits in
so continuing on with seeing abduction
from the light of active inference which
we might even operationalize as saying
like
framing or viewing abduction
from the perspective of the active
inference ontology
so rather than us
self-electing
as interpretance of active inference as
some
concept which we cannot necessarily
speak for a concept
we can't speak for english but we can
use english words
and so analogously we don't need to
necessarily speak for active inference
though i'm the last to say what those
should or shouldn't do
it's possible to
use the active inference ontology and
then it's kind of like a two-step
checklist
was the term in the act of inference
ontology in the core supplement or
entailed sections
was it used
in a way that was pragmatic that made
sense in that situation
in that multi-scale context
and that is actually a two-step process
to ask if we're speaking
using active inference rather than if
we're speaking for like an advocate or
like a salesperson for active inference
per se
and they're going to restate the case in
terms of the fap framework in the sense
of and using the terms of
and they're going to highlight the
relationship of internal states
to external states mediated through the
blanket
and they then go through this syllogism
and they restructure and restate their
qualitative schema of abductive active
inference
and they describe this
action cognition perception
loop
where
a surprisal any incoming
sensory information is experienced
and then
they take that not just into the passive
or even active interpretation of it
in the context of a bayesian generative
model
but rather something that is unfolding
in that mood of the investigant
they do continue on
and bring in uh important piercing idea
of the economy of research
so we'll go over this again hopefully
with authors
um it relates to pierce's theory of
science
pierce's original paper in 1970 or 1876
on the economy of research
wrote the doctrine of economy in general
treats the relationships between utility
and cost
and specifically that is going to be
related to research in this socially
enacted pragmatic sense
by asking how given expenditure of money
time and energy
what is
going to obtain the most valuable
addition to knowledge
what experiment that my eyes could
cicade to will have the most information
gain
what experiments could the researcher
carry out to reduce their uncertainty
the most about the natural system
not merely to verify something they know
not merely to falsify something that
they know will be falsified but rather
to exist in this optimal experimentation
space
and then pierce and later the authors
are going to naturalize contextualize
bring to the social cognitive area
by asking well how does money time and
energy happen because that optimal
experiment is in cultured and it uses
energy it uses reagents so perhaps in
this way we could say that pierce was
one of the first modern program managers
for a major funding agency but no he
wasn't and they discussed this economy
of research a bit more
they describe in this section
how pierce
promotes several
values or virtues or qualities
that characterize the economy of
scientific hypothesis making
in complexity
which is like a de-risking
breadth
which speaks to unification
and caution
as the economic quality of avoiding
diminishing marginal returns
by skillfully breaking down questions
into a series of small questions that
can be answered with reasonable limits
of investment
how many interesting threads are being
brought together
for example questions that are broken
down to binary yes no questions
can be connected to information theory
and quantum as well
here dean i will let you
speak to fairness
i'll just read it to be fair and as
briefly at the beginning of this paper
there are no instrumentalist
interpretations of fep and it's
ingredients such as markov blankets
but
this is a footnote in this paper but our
faith for one of a better word and
realist credentials of fep as its roots
in the pragma pragmatist optimism or
rather its act of ameliarism about the
gains from the alliance between
evolutionary evolutionarily useful
processes to contribute to maximizing
survival
if this pragmatist approach to realism
displeases the elevated taste of one who
looks for some staunch metaphysical
criteria let a thousand
flowers bloom i think what's fascinating
about this is that
to hold the idea that there is a realism
is a very easily defendable position to
take but even in the previous slide one
of the things that
that
first talked about without saying them
directly or at least not in those quotes
was that
that optimal position is some some
element of exploitation or economy
or simplicity or or somebody's done this
before me
is that a shortcut
and exploration which tends to take
longer has more
trial and error
but also doesn't have you constantly
over fitting
to a particular outcome
so
um
that's the reality
and again i wouldn't i wouldn't push
back on the claim that there is a very
real
piece to this
playing
play a minimum of two going back and
forth in this
um
so
i'm not just in fact i fully agree with
these authors like i fully agree with
the other authors about
about the idea of a co-construction so i
don't know that
you you you are
you are necessarily um confused if you
can say yes and yes and yes again
steven
yeah sort of adding to what being saying
there and
the idea of
implementation or
exploitation definitely is being alluded
to
and in science
there's
experimentation is sort of the way of
gaining knowledge
but there's the exploration piece and my
i would argue that
you can't get
exploration per se within
the kind of
objective domain there has to be this
journey into the into the into the
performative subjective into subjective
liminal
as einstein did with his mind games all
these and you create these sort of
mental uh constructs in a way what some
of what's happening today is a mixture
of that and then that's brought back
and modeled experimented with whatever
um
so i think there's a i mean modeling is
interesting because
it's uh it kind of can come on that
journey a little bit as well
so that's
that's could be something which
experiments can't do
here's a summary of an old joke person a
says a
and the referee says you're right person
b says b the referee says you're right
and person c says well a and b can't be
right and the referee says you know
you're right
it's a little rapid humor for those who
like that genre
um they then have a conclusion section
and
we have many questions and points to
make and a lot of connections to bring
back
to a lot of the naturalization here
like the fields in levin
work and they even take it to the
regenerative capacities of flatworms so
from
flat worms to flatmates
that's where we're going today
and then we also saved up for the dot
one
some of the juxtaposition of the markov
blanket concept specifically
the social and active components of
science which are super important and
majeed has brought on to these
discussions previously is a great point
of contact with the abductive paper and
the social inactive paper
markov blankets represent like a very
constrained even technical
contact front that will provide a lot of
discussion in the dot one
and that is where
we close the dot zero
with uh
again so much excellent groundwork and
backpack packing
by dean and steven so
is there anything else you'd like to add
at this point or anything arising that
you want to discuss in the dot one yes
dean then stephen if you'd like daniel
fantastic job we just did an order of
magnitude 3 from what was typically a
single paper live stream and we still
got it in under two hours so that you're
you're to be applauded for that and
secondly i just want to
as maybe as a bit of a tip off for the
dot one there's a research by the name
of israel israel nunez who talks about
if you want to be able to
look at how things are deconstructed and
constructed you have to look at both
product in process an example being how
do i build a car
and process in product
what is
what is the thing that either a
branching
point or an actual utensil
and so if you if you open your mind up
to both that inversion
along that continuum
it opens up all kinds of possibilities
in terms of bringing things into a place
where they don't necessarily come into
conflict yes they can integrate in braid
and so maybe that will be
after today
something that people who are using
active inference which in my opinion is
both product and process and process and
product
at the same time it's the gripper and
the grip maybe they'll maybe they will
give some thought over to them
it's almost like the pragmatist sees the
fork in the road and uses it
and maybe you use the fork by going one
way and maybe you do pick it up maybe
you use it by completing the table
setting for someone else who will dine
there and so there's so many ways to use
because use is
socially enacted abductive
contextualized etc
and again at the fork
is where that conversation is happening
and at our field site or at base camp is
where we can imagine the forks and the
roads that will come across stephen
yeah and next in the in the dot one sort
of finding a way
to
bring the authors if whoever's there you
know on a bit of a journey maybe down
one of the forks maybe it goes to the
edge of the lake and we need to get in
and get a bit wet
so how can scientific
abduction or some of the sort of more
scientifically bounded
models rules substantiated by
experimentation and instrumentation okay
when
when does that get moved away maybe
because of participation maybe because
of transdisciplinarity maybe because of
transformational processes maybe because
of deep exploration
outside of the field um i wonder this is
something you might want to think about
how can we
give
some sort of clear
journey options right so that they can
come
a little bit off without getting stuck
in a you know in quicksand or
drowning in the in in the deep water
right so we we want to sort of navigate
but i think this this is given
some of those um pointers i think of
where there is
sort of
waze off-ramps as well as on-ramps so
thanks
thank you fellows
thank you
this was huge i really really appreciate
all your help
great times see you in the doll one
you